<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Charles' Lab Notes</title>
    <link>https://notes.inclouds.space/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://notes.inclouds.space/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Charles' quick-to-publish notes</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
      <item>
        <title># 2022-05-31</title>
        <description>Well! An awesome day. It started out by installing ubuntu on a small desktop computer:

![](./static/2023-05-31-01.jpeg)

And then progressed to drilling holes into a vesa mount of a monitor arm:

![](./static/2023-05-31-03.jpeg)

Which let me position a webcam and projector in the air:

![](./static/2023-05-31-04.jpeg)

To finally project a blue square on my desk:

![](./static/2023-05-31-02.jpeg)

And what a blue square it is!

There were too many issues to count along the way. The computer I got ended up not having a wifi card built in but it did come with a usb wifi adapter. I spent altogether too much time manually downloading the debian packages needed to compile this adapter&#39;s firmware only to find out that it wasn&#39;t compatible with the latest linux kernel version. So I&#39;m getting a new wifi adapter shipped, but in the meantime I went to the store to buy an ethernet cable. This let me get started but wouldn&#39;t reach to the right desk, so I have ended up using phone&#39;s hotspot through a manual bluetooth connection. Which of course lead to more issues. My printer is configured to work on my home network which this desktop computer doesn&#39;t have access to (since it doesn&#39;t have a wifi card), so printing out four April tags involved alternating between my phone&#39;s hotspot to get a single print job queued and then my home network to actaully print it. A wild ride for sure!

But it should all be worth it, watching a new interface flicker to life.</description>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">inclouds-space-20220531</guid>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title># 2022-05-30</title>
        <description>I&#39;m in the process of setting up a [folk.computer](https://folk.computer) installation! Today involved running to the hardware store to buy clamps, eyewear, power strip, flash drive, etc. Tonight or tomorrow I&#39;ll start drilling: have to widen the holes in a monitor arm&#39;s VESA mount to let through the 1/4&quot; 20 screws that the projector and webcam use. I&#39;m hoping that the end result will be pretty clean!

Folk is a projector-camera &quot;physical computing&quot; interface and operating system developed by [Andrés](https://cwervo.com/) and [Omar](https://omar.website/). The idea is you position a camera and a projector above your desk and plug them into a computer with access to a printer. This setup lets you:

- use computer vision to track April Tags (kind of like QR codes but faster to recognize) in real time.
- project light onto and around the objects you are tracking, informed by information from the computer vision (position, rotation, skew of tags in space).
- print out sheets of paper with these April Tags, giving you the ability to bring new augmented objects into the world with ease.

I&#39;m extremely excited about this. Last week I witnessed a musical performance where someone with no particular training manipulated 5 pieces of paper to create a musical experience. This is how we seamlessly empower non-technical humans with technology: extraodinarily easy, high-bandwith interfaces you can **play** with.

Stay posted.</description>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">inclouds-space-20220530</guid>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title># 2022-05-29</title>
        <description>I added links on each header here! Had to use pandoc&#39;s gfm_auto_identifiers extension and then used a [lua filter](https://pandoc.org/lua-filters.html) to add the actual links to the header. This was an updated version of [the filter](https://github.com/jgm/pandoc-website/blob/master/tools/anchor-links.lua) pandoc uses for its own documentation.

```lua
function Header(h)
  if h.identifier ~= &#39;&#39; then
    local anchor_link = pandoc.Link(
      h.content,                        -- content
      &#39;#&#39; .. h.identifier,              -- href
      &#39;&#39;,                               -- title
      { class = &#39;header-anchor&#39; }       -- attributes
    )
    h.content = anchor_link
    return h
  end
end
```</description>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">inclouds-space-20220529</guid>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title># 2022-05-28</title>
        <description>I&#39;ve added an RSS feed for these notes! I&#39;m using pandoc to render a single markdown file into html, so had to figure out some way to get an rss feed as well. I went with a ruby script to parse the markdown and generate the xml on build. Turned out to be easier than I was expecting!

See the feed here: [./rss.xml](./rss.xml)</description>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">inclouds-space-20220528</guid>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title># 2022-05-27</title>
        <description>## Motivation

Well I&#39;ve been doing some long-form writing on my [blog](https://inclouds.space/blog) and I&#39;ve enjoyed it. But the format necessitates a lot of editing and care, at least in my mind. This can be good for me—practicing writing long form pieces and the editing that goes with that—but it&#39;s not easy and often either prevents me from getting content out or seriously delays it. I&#39;d like to be able to share spure of the moment insights and snippets easily and quickly, in the hopes that I end up getting a larger amount of content out and in public. That too is good practice!

So please bear with me; thoughts might not be as fully-formed, spelling might not be well-checked, grammer will be mid at best. This is an experiment! I&#39;m hoping the content itself can earn its keep despite these potential pitfalls.

Also I like exclamation points and will probably use more of them here than my normal blog! No more censorship!


## Forest

As I add these lab notes to the nav of my main site, they are replacing a link to my &quot;forest&quot; — an attempt at a digital garden I made a few months ago. Recently it has become less of a garden and more of a small, static grove of trees. So instead of pointing to it so directly, I&#39;m moving the link here. Please enjoy! [forest.inclouds.space](https://forest.inclouds.space/)</description>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">inclouds-space-20220527</guid>
      </item>

  </channel>
</rss>
